

+56 934812794

Rene Silva

DBA & Data Engineer

Ex Walmart + 10 Years integrating data

Data Engineer & DBA at The Hackett Group Inc.

Computer Engineer – Universidad de Santiago

TI Project Manager certified – Universidad de Chile

Now: DBA and **Data Engineer** → **Next Level:** Improving Data Scientist and Bilingual skills.

Data Skills → ETL/Java & Python Developer, Scraping, Consuming REST APIs, Multi CLOUD.

Newest Skills → Learning Devops / Learning Sensors and IOT data capture / Learning Apache Airflow.

Total 18 years of experience in:

Application Development/Analytics/DBA/Data Engineering Insurance / Retail / Commercial Centers / Financial

5+ years at **HDI Insurance**/Development JAVA + Oracle as **Developer**.

10+ years at Walmart, 5+ as Analytics Data Engineer - Customer Intelligence/GEO Analyst and 5+ as Senior DBA.

1+ year at **Commercial centers**, principal Chilean Mall company as **Data Engineer**.

2+ years with Global Enterprise Data, Cloud Warehouses/ Data Lakes /Smart Tools as Senior DBA and Data Engineer.

Principal Skills: DBA, Data Engineer, Integrator/Migrator - JAVA/Python/PHP.

Geo Tools: Geo-Graphical Reports, Geo-KPIs, Geo Share (Walmart).

Other skills: Database Entity Relation Dev/Object Oriented OOP.

Scraper/Crawlers developer, REST APIs/ERP/CRM data consumer to populate databases.

Integrator between database flavors and clouds, obtaining business advantages and saving space and money.

Soft skills: Thinking out of the box.

Experience training people and programmers mentoring on new techs.

Experience working with managers, integrating new techs to business cases.

Clouds: GCP (1 year), AWS (2 year), AZURE(3 years).

Please read my recommendations on LinkedIn → https://www.linkedin.com/in/rsilcas/

SKILLS

Platforms					
GCP	AWS	Azure	Alibaba	Linux	WIN
Technologies					
JAVA J2EE	Python	C language	Data Engineer	Talend	DBA
STRUTS	Django	C# C++ Lang	SSIS Integration	DataStage	SQL
HTML	Flask	Visual Basic	PowerCenter	Learning AirFlow	Analysis Services
Javascript	BeautifulSoap	Powershell	DataFactory	PHP-GEO Tools	OLAP Cubes
Databases					
SQL Server	Snowflake	Oracle	Teradata	PostgreSQL	AWS Aurora
Others					
Scrapers	Crawlers	Voice Bots	Speech – recog.	Softaculous	UIPATH
Data Distribution	AWS EC2	AWS S3	-	-	Automation
Languages					

Native Spanish, English Intermediate moving to advanced.

WORK EXPERIENCE

TheHackettGroup.com (Last Job) Senior DBA- Data Engineer - SubContractor from Miami

Montevideo, Uruguay (Remote from Chile) (2021/03 – 2022/06)

The Hackett Group.com, managing and updating databases on **SQLServer** – Microsoft databases.

Others BigDATA: **Snowflake** – WebCrawler creation with drilldowns on some links.

Others OLTP: Oracle, managing global databases Brookfield.com, Edgewell.com, Energizer and Garmin.

During this time I participated in the following projects:

Project: Company Master Database <u>www.Data.ai</u> (2021/11 - 2022/06)

The project goal is obtaining a complete company master database with the trademarks hierarchy. Main tasks executed in the project:

- Creation of the custom WebCrawler to Data.ai team, this tool will be used to obtain the brand hierarchy of the application publishers and companies, databases: Google Apps and IOs Apps.
- I designed and implemented the solution from scratch, delivering diagrams all weeks and sprints.
 - o Solution: Object Oriented Programing model and class diagram.
 - o Snowflake database: ER diagram delivered on HTML.
- SCRUM mode, with Daily meetings and this was my first project 100% in English.
- Produce RAW data to the Data Scientist teams, to create/train the hierarchy algorithms.

Saving money on S3 Buckets, navigating 2.4 million webpages using memory and parallelism, avoiding FILE creation and costs related to storage, even the times was improved without file writing/reading.

Technologies: AMAZON, AWS, S3 Buckets, SNOWFLAKE, BDP (some PySpark), mainly Python on Crawlers.

Database management: Global databases (2021/03 – 2022/06)

Mainly focused on backup standardization and restoring from/to DEV/QA/PROD.

Main tasks executed in the project was on Brookfield, Edgewell, Energizer, Garmin, AstraZeneca.

- Azure Databases: Moving data between old platforms, from/to Azure.
- Tunning/Improvements on query times.
- Installations/Migrations, Patching/Fixing vulnerabilities on SQLServer 2008/2012/2014/2019.
- Moving, detecting, and shutting down unused databases SQLServer 2005/2008.

I was improving the standards of backup/restoring databases between environments.

I was updating documentation about installations, migrating and turning-off obsolete databases.

Technologies: Amazon Aurora, flavor POSTGRE, AWS Lambda Functions/ S3 Buckets, ORACLE/SQLSERVER on premise.

MallPlaza Chile

Huechuraba, Chile (2019- 2020)

Position: Data Engineer

Falabella Group is the Principal Mall enterprise of Chile, containing cinemas, supermarkets, fast food services and entertainment parks, the focus of the Analytical teams is understand the customer behavior, the Tenants occupation, the people flows using the Parking data and sensors inside the mall.

During this time I participated in the following projects:

Project: Parking Data Normalization and Dashboards (2019 – 2020)

The principal focus of this was understand the flows and show those reports to the commercial areas to take decisions, and my first step is clean the RAW data, create and validate INFO with other sources.

Main tasks executed in the related projects:

- I was Cleaning/Moving/Improving quality data.
- I created dashboards of all Commercial categories of the company to understand the flows by mall.
- With SAP info maintaining the database updated, focused on the Store count by category/commercial groups, answering questions like: how many McDonalds we have? by mall? evolution? by month? 24 months?
- People Flow: Sensor's data (Spanish provider): Managing information of stores and people flow inside the mall, by floor/sensor zone/brand/store/month/mall/country predicting the future flow using linear regressions.

The principal goals were: Maintain all parking data in one place, **GCP BigQuery**, detecting malls without data in SQLServers, creating flow dashboards in a graphic way by GCP reports.

Technologies: Google GCP, GCP Bigquery, Postgre, SQLServer, JAVA, Python, DataStage.

Walmart Chile
Position: Senior DBA - Microsoft

Huechuraba, Chile (2013/09 – 2018/09) (Remote 2 days at week)

Principal Retailer of Chile, near 40% of Share on supermarkets, Walmart is worldwide company, near 500+ stores in Chile. On this position I was on charge of all Microsoft databases, migrating and shutting down Oracle databases.

Administering TERADATA, near 12 TeraBytes and Microsoft Parallel datawarehouse near 14 TeraBytes.

During this time I participated in the following projects:

Project: All projects that include DATA (2013 – 2018)

I was on near 20+ projects because the DBA and the DATA exist on almost every development project. Main tasks executed in those projects:

- Being critical with the solutions, for example I was on the role to SAY NO if the system proposed by the developer teams is not being secure with data, of all supermarkets: LIDER, ACUENTA, EXPRESS.
- Proposing solutions and moving the developer teams to the Walmart International standards on all new projects, using in some cases distribution, replications in different cities and with at least 4 providers on 24/7 roles on monitoring, and I was on charge to prevent and solve database incidents.
- AZURE Virtual Machines and Azure databases: Shutting down a lot of obsolete machines with vulnerabilities, like
 WIN2003, SQL2005, ORACLE9 and 10.
- In some cases, helping the developer teams to improve queries and detecting bottle necks.

Maintain all databases working well and adding value with high availability solutions like ALLWAYS ON. Technologies: **Teradata**, Microsoft Parallel Datawarehouse, SQLSERVER, OLAP Cubes in MOLAP and ROLAP modes.

Walmart Chile Quilicura, Chile Position: CRM – Project Manager – GEO Analyst (2008 – 2013)

During this time I participated in the following projects:

Project: GEO Tool – Google Earth (2013 – 2018)

Real State: Being smart on new openings, selecting the best zone of a group of possible projects, this business process occurs near 1 or 2 years before the store opens.

Obtain GEO Reports reporting to: Real State Manager: creation a good smart tool to real state analysts to prevent **CANNIBALIZATION** between stores using the loyalty program data and other sources on the model.

Main tasks executed in the project:

- I was on charge to create from scratch: data model, demo, selecting the provider and mentoring a little team of 3 developers and the production deployment.
- Database of stores, using data of business areas (Commercial and Real State) with existing and future stores of the 3 principal trademarks of Walmart in Chile: LIDER, ACUENTA, EXPRESS.
- Creating queries and Obtaining Pre-calculated data indexed with the Geo Locations.
- Report of the people leaving Walmart Stores, joined with Life Cycle and Value Segmentations / other KPIs.

This is my best, complex and biggest system, 6.4+ millions of customers and 10+ TB in transactions of 3+ years of history of 500+ stores and 50+future store projects.

Reports: Evolution of the Count of customers on the zone, selected by the Real State specialist, generating Excel and map detailed, store by store.

Technologies: Teradata, JAVA, PHP, KML Standard, Google Earth, Google Maps, Informatica PowerCenter.

HDI Insurance is a enterprise focused on Car Insurance, previous name was Aseguradora Magallanes, the customer can buy a policy ensuring one Car and one Motorcicle on the same contract, but taking a lot of time on the contract typing and deliver, then the solution was focused on save time.

Project: Policy Production System (2005 – 2006)

The focus is writing more contracts in less time.

Main tasks executed in the project:

- Design of a new web-based system, using J2EE enterprise patterns.
- Build a responsive web application with AJAX and avoiding submit forms.
- The user can create a new contract using previous data steps, using less fields can populate faster the form and save time, this increased the policy production.

The major contribution was SAVE TIME and produce more policies. Other contribution was the creation of the renovation concept, and the customer can obtain the contract at the same day. The principal difficult was the payment systems, then we created a solution automatically creating dues and payment plan.

Technologies: JAVA, J2EE, Struts, AJAX, ORACLE.

Project: Sinister and Integration with oldest systems (2006 –2008)

This project was oriented to the customer and to the user: Policy **LIQUIDATOR**.

Focused on the accidents and their logs, photos, etc. mainly finding the nearest/cheaper/warranty provider to fix the car, estimating costs and other information related to the spare parts, this was integrating with other enterprise areas and provider integration with API Rest Services.

Main tasks executed in the project:

- Integrate the Sinister system re-using the Production data, using XML in NO-RELATIONAL mode.
- Populate the forms automatically when the user has some accident, improving the customer/liquidator views and times, choosing the next step/provider/workshop to fix the car.

The major contribution was with the car-providers integration and in second place with the mechanic's workshops when the customer has an accident and needs to repair the car improving service times.

Technologies: JAVA, J2EE, Struts, AJAX, ORACLE.

EDUCATION

Period	Name	Entity
2000 – 2005	Computer Engineer	Universidad de Santiago de Chile
2008 – 2008	Project Manager	Universidad de Chile
2010 - 2010	SQL Server Database	Quintec/Microsoft
2010 - 2010	SQL Server Integration	Quintec/Microsoft
2015 – 2018	Soft Skills, Mentoring/English	Walmart
2017 – 2017	Networking	Sonda/CISCO

HOBBIES

Wind instruments	Robotics	Family
Flutes (a lot)	Arduino Cards	Beach with my wife
Soprano Sax	Speech bots	Play Games with my children
Alto Sax	Joke bot (Python)	Cycling (alone)